<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<esp:page xmlns:esp="http://oracc.org/ns/esp/1.0" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" xmlns:xh="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" xmlns:xpd="http://oracc.org/ns/xpd/1.0">
  <esp:name>Corpus</esp:name>
  <esp:title>Corpus</esp:title>
  <html>
    <head/>
    <body>
      <p>The PC text Corpus is defined by the CDLI corpus of
      Proto-Cuneiform texts of Uruk IV and Uruk III data, as adapted
      for use by PCSL: we call this <code>CDLI-tc</code>; note that
      CDLI-tc is used here only in the PCSL version of the
      corpus. This version has some minor modifications to the
      transliteration and has been converted to use Unicode
      transliteration conventions rather than the CDLI ASCII ones.</p>

      <p>There are 5976 texts in the corpus of which 1752 are
      attributed to Uruk IV and 4224, or roughly 75% of the corpus, to
      the subsequent Uruk III period.</p>

      <esp:sh>The Digital Corpus</esp:sh>
      <p>The digital corpus includes the contents of the following major publications:</p>
      <ul>
	<li>Uruk lexical tablets from ATU3 (Uruk IV and Uruk III)</li>
	<li>Uruk administrative tablets from ATU5, ATU6, ATU7 (Uruk IV and Uruk III);
	these supercede ATU1</li>
	<li>Jemdet Nasr (Uruk III) tablets from MSVO1; these supercede
	Langdon, PI</li>
	<li>Tablets from various locations from MSVO4; this includes
	non-Uruk tablets which were included in ATU1</li>
	<li>Tablets in private collections from various locations in
	CUSAS1, CUSAS21, and CUSAS31; these post-date the ATU and MSVO
	volumes</li>
	<li>Tablets from the "Erlenmeyer Collection"; these were to be
	published in MSVO3 which has not yet appeared; many of them
	have been edited by Englund and others in various
	publications, however</li>
	<!--<li>Tablets in private collections primarily from Umma; these
	are in the CDLI set of transliterations but have not yet been
	edited in print</li>-->
      </ul>

      <esp:sh>The Composition of the Corpus</esp:sh>

      <p>PCSL's version of CDLI-tc has the following composition
      divided by provenience, period, and published/unpublished
      status:</p>

      <table class="pretty" width="70%">
	<tr>
	  <td/>
	  <td>IV/pub</td>
	  <td>IV/unp</td>
	  <td>IV/all</td>
	  <td>III/pub</td>
	  <td>III/unp</td>
	  <td>III/all</td>
	</tr>
	<tr>
	  <td>Uruk</td>
	  <td>1205</td>
	  <td>548</td>
	  <td>1753 </td>
	  <td>1895</td>
	  <td>935</td>
	  <td>2830</td>
	</tr>
	<tr>
	  <td>JN</td>
	  <td>0</td>
	  <td>0</td>
	  <td>0 </td>
	  <td>237</td>
	  <td>0</td>
	  <td>237</td>
	</tr>
	<tr>
	  <td>Umma</td>
	  <td>0</td>
	  <td>0</td>
	  <td>0 </td>
	  <td>112</td>
	  <td>295</td>
	  <td>407</td>
	</tr>
	<tr>
	  <td>Uqair</td>
	  <td>0</td>
	  <td>0</td>
	  <td>0 </td>
	  <td>42</td>
	  <td>0</td>
	  <td>42</td>
	</tr>
	<tr>
	  <td>Misc</td>
	  <td>33</td>
	  <td>16</td>
	  <td>49 </td>
	  <td>609</td>
	  <td>49</td>
	  <td>658</td>
	</tr>
	<tr>
	  <td>total</td>
	  <td>1238</td>
	  <td>564</td>
	  <td>1802 </td>
	  <td>2895 </td>
	  <td>1279</td>
	  <td>4174</td>
	</tr>
      </table>

    </body>
  </html>
</esp:page>
