<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<esp:page xmlns:esp="http://oracc.org/ns/esp/1.0"
	  xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
	  xmlns:xh="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
	  xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <esp:name>Corpus</esp:name>
  <esp:title>Corpus</esp:title>
  <html>
    <head/>
    <body>
      <p>The PC text Corpus is defined by the CDLI corpus of
      Proto-Cuneiform texts of Uruk IV and Uruk III data, as adapted
      for use by PCSL: we call this <code>CDLI-tc</code>; note that
      CDLI-tc is used here only in the PCSL version of the
      corpus. This version has some minor modifications to the
      transliteration and has been converted to use Unicode
      transliteration conventions rather than the CDLI ASCII ones.</p>

      <p>There are <xi:include xml:base="."
      href="../../texts/tpcsl/c.cnt" parse="text"/> texts in the
      corpus of which <xi:include xml:base="."
      href="../../texts/tpcsl/c-4.cnt" parse="text"/> are attributed
      to Uruk IV and <xi:include xml:base="."
      href="../../texts/tpcsl/c-3.cnt" parse="text"/>, to the
      subsequent Uruk III period.</p>

      <esp:sh>The Print Corpus</esp:sh>

      <p>The principle modern publications of the Proto-Cuneiform corpus are:</p>
      
      <dl>
	<dt>ZATU</dt>
	<dd>M.W. Green, Nissen, H. <i>Zeichenliste der Archaischen Texte aus Uruk</i>, ATU 2, Berlin 1987.</dd>

	<dt>ATU3</dt>
	<dd>R.K. Englund und Nissen, H., unter Mitarbeit von Peter Damerow,
	"Die Lexikalischen Listen der Archaischen Texte aus Uruk" (ATU 3), Berlin 1993.</dd>

	<dt>ATU5</dt>
	<dd>R.K. Englund, <i>Archaic Administrative Texts from Uruk:
	The Early Campaigns</i>, ATU 5, Berlin 1994.</dd>

	<dt>ATU6</dt>
	<dd>R.K. Englund and Nissen, H., <i>>Archaische Verwaltungs-
	texte aus Uruk: Vorderasiatische Museum II</i>, ATU 6, Berlin 2005.</dd>

	<dt>ATU7</dt>
	<dd>R.K. Englund and Nissen, H., <i>Archaische Verwaltungs-
	texte aus Uruk: Die Heidelberger Sammlung</i>, ATU 7, Berlin
	2001.</dd>

	<dt>MSVO1</dt>
	<dd>R.K. Englund and Grégoire, J.-P., <i>The Proto-Cuneiform
	Texts from Jemdet Nasr</i>, MSVO 1, Berlin 1991.</dd>

	<dt>MSVO3</dt>
	<dd>R.K. Englund, <i>The Proto-Cuneiform Texts from the
	Erlenmeyer Collection</i>, MSVO 3, Berlin forthcoming.</dd>
	
	<dt>MSVO4</dt>
	<dd>R.K. Englund, <i>Proto-Cuneiform Texts from Diverse Collections</i>, MSVO 4, Berlin 1996.</dd>

	<dt>CUSAS01</dt>
	<dd>S.F. Monaco, The Cornell University Archaic Tablets (CUSAS 1), Bethesda, MD, 2007.</dd>

	<dt>CUSAS21</dt>
	<dd>S.F. Monaco, Archaic Bullae and Tablets in the Cornell
        University Collections (CUSAS 21), Bethesda, MD, 2014.</dd>
	
	<dt>CUSAS31</dt>
	<dd>S.F. Monaco, Archaic Cuneiform Tablets from Private Collections (CUSAS 31), Bethesda, MD, 2016.</dd>
      </dl>
      
      <esp:sh>The Digital Corpus</esp:sh>
      
      <p>The digital corpus includes the contents of the all of the
      above major publications:</p>
      
      <ul>
	<li>Uruk lexical tablets from ATU3 (Uruk IV and Uruk III)</li>
	<li>Uruk administrative tablets from ATU5, ATU6, ATU7 (Uruk IV and Uruk III);
	these supercede ATU1</li>
	<li>Jemdet Nasr (Uruk III) tablets from MSVO1; these supercede
	Langdon, PI</li>
	<li>Tablets from various locations from MSVO4; this includes
	non-Uruk tablets which were included in ATU1</li>
	<li>Tablets in private collections from various locations in
	CUSAS1, CUSAS21, and CUSAS31; these post-date the ATU and MSVO
	volumes</li>
	<li>Tablets from the "Erlenmeyer Collection"; these were to be
	published in MSVO3 which has not yet appeared; many of them
	have been edited by Englund and others in various
	publications, however</li>
	<!--<li>Tablets in private collections primarily from Umma; these
	are in the CDLI set of transliterations but have not yet been
	edited in print</li>-->
      </ul>
      
      <esp:sh>PCSL Corpus</esp:sh>

      <p>PCSL's version of CDLI-tc has the following composition
      divided by provenience, period, and published/unpublished
      status:</p>

      <xi:include xml:base="." href="../../texts/tpcsl/corpus.html"/>

      <esp:sh>PC25 Corpus</esp:sh>

      <p>About 1/3 of the PCSL corpus is available only in
      transliteration or photograph and has not yet been subjected to
      the rigorous assessment of a scholarly edition. These texts are
      removed to create a subcorpus of well-studied text to serve as
      the basis for the initial (and largest) phase of encoding of
      Proto-Cuneiform.</p>

      <p>The subsetting is based on the CDLI catalogue entries as of
      February 2025.  It is possible that features of the CDLI data
      may mean that a few texts that should have been omitted are
      included in the PC25 corpus and vice versa. The impact of this
      on the final repertoire is neglible, however, because of the
      cross-checking between corpus and published sign lists.</p>
      
      <p>PC25's subset of the PCSL corpus has the following
      composition divided by provenience, period, and
      published/unpublished status:</p>

      <xi:include xml:base="." href="../../texts/tpc25/corpus.html"/>

      <esp:sh>ED I-II Excluded from the Proposal</esp:sh>

      <p>It is generally recognized that there is a group of about 400
      texts from the site of Ur which are later than Proto-Cuneiform
      but earlier than the ED IIIa corpus from Fara (Šuruppak): these
      are conventionally assigned to the Early Dynastic I-II period.
      There are also about two dozen tablets and fragments from Uruk
      that are assigned to the same period (Green; LeCompte nXXX).</p>

      <p>Texts and signs from this period are excluded from the
      proto-cuneiform proposal.</p>

      <p>In Englund's exhaustive discussion of the Archaic texts, he
      includes this period in his concluding remarks as the 8th phase
      of proto-cuneiform:</p>

      <blockquote>8. <i>Period of late proto-cuneiform</i>
        <br/>
	Ca. 2800-2700 B.C. (Early Dynastic 1), this period is
	characterized by the earliest apparently multivalent use of
	proto-cuneiform to write Sumerian words in personal names.
	The archaic numerical systems were used, but in simplified
	forms, and the lexical lists were copied and transmitted, but
	no new lists were added. Tablets were as a rule clumsily
	formed and inscribed. (Englund OBO 160/1 [1998], p.215).
      </blockquote>

      <p>Appearing about 15 years later, LeCompte and Verderame's
      edition of ED I-II fragments from Ur observed that there are key
      features of the writing system that depart from the earlier PC
      practices, and by analysis of both personal names and the
      contexts of the texts that they are written in Sumerian
      language:</p>

      <blockquote>We decided to follow in the transliteration the system that is
      commonly accepted for Sumerian, thus in small type and in
      accordance with the values of the signs available on the e-PSD
      website or in aBZL. We did not adopt the codes applied to the
      archaic texts from Uruk and Jemdet Nasr, although the
      transliteration available for lexical tablets in ATU 310 follows
      such a system for the ED I-II period. This choice is justified
      by the fact that the signs in the texts from Ur do not seem to
      present the same variants as their archaic forerunners: for
      example, the different shapes of E₂ cannot be classified into
      E₂~a, E₂~b...; furthermore, some signs have no variant, such as
      DU₈, which is always drawn according to a standard and well
      known shape. Second, as the language of these texts is
      undoubtedly Sumerian, it would have been unnecessary to use such
      values: instead of writing such cumbersome transliterations as
      DUB~a-LU₂-NU-ŠE₃ or EN~a-GAN~a-GI4~a, it was accordingly more
      convenient to propose directly Mes-lu₂-nu-še₃ and
      En-ḫe₂-gi₄. (LeCompte and Verderame 2014, p.4)</blockquote>

      <p>Another factor which marks the ED I-II corpus as transitional
      between Uruk III/Jemdet Nasr and ED IIIa is the organization and
      structure of tablets.  In a thorough survey of these
      "diplomatics", LeCompte, based on the work of the original
      editor of the ED I-II corpus from Ur, Burrows, summarizes the
      situation as follows:</p>

      <blockquote>As Burrows has already noted, archaic texts from Ur are intermediate in nature.
Features common with Late Uruk/Jemdet Nasr tablets include:<br/>
– an oblong shape, half rounded sides, larger tablets having a rectangular format.<br/>
– a reverse generally left uninscribed.<br/>
– the presence of clauses and subscripts freely disposed apart from or into the
columns.<br/>
– tablets from Ur displaying rows of lines inconsistent with the usual columns; this
clearly comes from the horizontal lines subdivided into columns observable in a
few of the Jemdet Nasr texts.<br/>
<br/>
On the other hand, the ED I–II texts are forerunners to the ED III tablets in regard to
the following aspects:
– surface, with a rather flat obverse and convex reverse.<br/>
– a lack of subdivision of cases similar to the Late Uruk period.<br/>
– total expressed as gu₂-an-še₃.<br/>
<br/>
Other features are very specific to the ED I–II period, such as the clumsy form of many
tablets and the random disposition of columns. (LeCompte 2016: 142).</blockquote>

      <p>After discussion among the proposal authors and Robin LeRoy,
      we have determined that it is preferable to establish the end of
      the Uruk III period as the cutoff for Unicode PC encoding, and
      to assign the ED I-II signiary to Sumero-Akkadian Cuneiform.</p>

      <esp:ssh>PC signs in ED I-II</esp:ssh>
      
      <p>For characters that occur only in Proto-Cuneiform and ED
      I-II, we do not propose to encode the character twice; instead,
      as with the Archaic Cuneiform Numbers, we propose to treat
      isolated PC signs in ED I-II texts as archaic holdovers.</p>

      <p>Signs which occur only in ED I-II texts will be evaluated for
      encoding in SAC in the future, as will signs that first occur in
      ED I-II and recur in later periods.</p>
      
    </body>
  </html>
</esp:page>
