<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<esp:page xmlns:esp="http://oracc.org/ns/esp/1.0" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" xmlns:xh="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" xmlns:xpd="http://oracc.org/ns/xpd/1.0">
  <esp:name>Principles</esp:name>
  <esp:title>Revised Principles for Encoding Proto-Cuneiform</esp:title>
  <html>
    <head/>
    <body>

      <esp:h>Principles for Encoding</esp:h>

      <p>Each character that occurs in the PC25 subset of the PCSL
      corpus has been assessed according to the following principles
      in order to determine its encodability.  Encoded signs are given
      in Appendix A and B; the condensed version of the
      Proto-Cuneiform Sign List, PCSL, is given Appendix C and
      contains essential information relating to the encodability of
      each sign.  Appendix D lists all of the manuscripts that have
      unencoded signs and the signs which they are missing. Appendices
      E to K give tables of signs excluded from PC25 under one of the
      reasons for which they were excluded.</p>

      <p>In addition to the comments above on the corpus, signiary,
      and sign lists, some additional issues influence the Principles.</p>
      
      <esp:sh>(Non-)Constrastive Usage</esp:sh>

      <p>Previous proposals treated the whole of CDLI-gh as a flat
      sample of sign forms and assigned codepoints to each form.  All
      of the resources, however, are highly consistent in listing and
      transliterating some variant sign forms as non-contrastive and
      this practice is followed in PC25: the grouping of sign forms
      under a sign sign name and the practice of transliterating
      variant sign forms with a single transliteration are both
      indicators of non-contrastive glyphs.</p>

      <p>The scholarly assessment of when sign forms are
      non-contrastive is based on several kinds of evidence. There is
      a often a historical dimension where Uruk IV (earlier) and Uruk
      III (later) forms are presumptively of the same sign: Uruk IV
      forms tend to have more curves and more complex shapes.  For
      many signs, this analysis is assisted by duplicate manuscripts
      of word lists ("lexical texts") that give the same text with
      variant sign forms.  Elsewhere, commodity lists of phrasal
      constructs can give contextual information on the likelihood
      that two distinct forms actually belong to the same sign.</p>
      
      <p>Transliteration practices in the CDLI corpus closely mirror
      the contrastive/non-contrastive distinction.  For example, the
      SAG sign has several different glyph forms but is always
      transliterated <code>SAG</code>.  Conversely, <code>KUŠU₂</code>
      is a base name that has six different allographs,
      <code>KUŠU₂~a</code> to <code>KUŠU~f</code>: each of these
      allographs has instances in the corpus.</p>

      <esp:ssh>(Non-)Contrastive Usage in Complex and Compound Signs</esp:ssh>

      <p>CDLI-tc and CDLI-gh do not always differentiate compound
      constituents to the same extent as the independent versions of
      the constituents.  For example, KAR₂ is separated as KAR₂~a and
      KAR₂~b in CDLI-tc and CDLI-gh, but in the DARA₃×KAR₂ compounds
      the only notations that occur are |DARA₃~c×KAR₂| and
      |DARA₃~d×KAR₂|.  The encoding by default follows the CDLI
      notations in such cases.</p>

      <esp:sh>Sequences</esp:sh>

      <p>Sequences are a class of compound signs which exhibit a low
      degree of integration with each other.  In later cuneiform they
      are written as a linear sequence in which the constituents and
      order may vary.  In PC, they are written in linear form or as a
      cluster because PC accounts are laid out in various combinations
      of cases (or boxes).</p>

      <p>The identification of a group of signs as a discrete sequence
      can vary from one text editor to another, and from one sign list
      to another.  As a result, sequences are a variable and
      open-ended category which are not suited to encoding as
      characters.  If a sequence such as |MUŠEN.ŠE| were encoded as a
      character there would be two reasonable representations of the
      data: the character encoding, and the encoding as the sequence
      of consituents.</p>

      <p>The handling of sequences in PCSL--including a list of
      exceptions which are acutally encoded--is described in a
      separate section later in this document.</p>
      
      <esp:sh>Principles</esp:sh>

      <p>The principal imperatives are:</p>
      
      <ol>
 	<li>Treat the PC corpus as the primary source of truth about
 	the signiary and usage.  Use the corpus as a control on
 	the lists; use the published lists and corpus as a control on
 	CDLI-gh.</li>

	<li>Align names with CDLI-tc/CDLI-gh as much as possible to
	ensure that the encoding is closely aligned with existing
	scholarly practice. Make exceptions where required to correct
	names or to improve consistency of the naming scheme; if in
	doubt, retain the CDLI names.</li>
	
   	<li>Take contrastive usage into account to the extent
   	supported by contemporary scholarship and do not encode
   	non-contrastive sign variants under their own codepoints.  The
   	CDLI-tc corpus is the primary guide to non-constrastive usage:
   	different sign forms which are transliterated the same are
   	accepted as non-contrastive.</li>

	<li>Accept that allograph notations in the corpus are
	contrastive</li>
	
	<li>Do not introduce finer-grained allograph notations than
	CDLI-tc/CDLI-gh is using.  The decisions made in the corpus
	about whether sign variants are contrastive or not are made
	not only on the basis of form but also context of various
	kinds; specialists in the corpus should decide if further
	division is needed in the future</li>

	<li>Do not require a minimum number of occurrences for
	encoding: the corpus consists of mostly fragmentary
	manuscripts over 5000 years old--if a sign clearly exists and
	meets the other principles for encoding, it should be
	encoded</li>

   	<li>Do not assume that every sign list entry should be encoded
   	as a character</li>

	<li>Do not generally encode sequences; this includes sequences
	which are named in CDLI-gh and CDLI-tc as single characters
	("opaque sequences") but where the naming is an interpretive
	mnemonic for a sign group such as <code>ŠAB</code> for
	<code>|PA.IB|</code> and the like</li>

	<li>Do make exceptions to the sequences rule for items which:
	<ul>
	  <li>are not historically sequences but are later decomposed,
	  e.g., some city names</li>
	  <li>would require the encoding of separate constituent
	  characters for a single case</li>
	  <li>form part of a group which contains a mixture of members
	  where some members might otherwise be encoded as characters
	  and others as sequence</li>
	</ul></li>

	<li>Consider distribution of components when encoding complex
	(X×Y) versus compound (X.Y or Y.X); sometimes, especially for
	rare signs, it is not clear whether the juxtaposition of
	components is part of the sign structure or the distribution
	of individual elements on the manuscript. In such cases it is
	preferable to treat the signs as a sequence rather than a
	complex.</li>
	
	<li>Do not separately encode signs which occur only in
	complex signs</li>

	<li>Do not encode uncertain signs, especially those from
	unedited texts such as the Schoyen Umma material</li>

	<li>Do not encode broken signs; include them in the PUA
	instead.</li>
      </ol>

      <esp:sh>Advantages of the Revised Approach</esp:sh>

      <p>There are several advantages to the revised approach to PC encoding:</p>
      
      <ul>
   	<li>the encoding is better aligned with transliteration
   	practice</li>
	
	<li>additional glyph variants can be added without impacting
	the encoding; encoding every glyph variant would open PC to
	arbitrary open-ended encoding of slight differences with
	little basis for distinguishing when a variant should be
	encoded and when not: adopting the position that scholarly
	annotation of glyph variance as contrastive is required for
	encoding would set reasonable boundaries on what can be
	encoded and what should not be</li>
	
 	<li>new sequences can be added without impacting the
 	encoding; this is especially important for the productive
 	types involving N57 and time notations involving U₄</li>

 	<li>variant forms can be managed with font features rather
 	than needing encoding</li>

	<li>the approach is generally more robust in regard to future
	discoveries as a result of the above points; where absolutely
	necessary unifications/disunifications could be considered if
	they are clearly demonstrable improvements to the utility of
	the encoding</li>
	
      </ul>
      
      <esp:sh>Reference Glyphs</esp:sh>

      <p>The introduction of 1:several relationships where an
      encoded character has multiple variants entails the need for a
      principled selection of reference glyphs.</p>

      <p>In order to have some level of consistency it would be
      preferable to select either Uruk IV glyphs or Uruk III glyphs
      as the primary choice of reference glyphs.  Because the corpus
      is predominantly Uruk III in date it makes sense to use Uruk
      III reference glyphs as far as possible.</p>

      <p>PC25 reference glyphs are aligned where possible with Uruk
      III sign forms occurring in published texts originating from
      Uruk or Jemdet Nasr. The selection of the reference glyph is not
      necessarily an indication that the other sign forms in EASL do
      not occur in the same period or place.  It means simply that the
      reference glyph has been confirmed to occur, where possible, in
      Uruk III Uruk/Jemdet Nasr.</p>

      <p>For sequences with multiple forms, the reference form is
      always the simplest/closest to the sequence description, as long
      as that form occurs in the corpus.  This means that by default
      the sign looks the way it is described, and ligatures,
      reorderings, or non-linear dispositions are always accessed by
      CVNN.</p>

      <p>Note that the selection of a reference glyph does not imply
      that the form is normative--the corpus is restricted and sign
      form variation is considerable which means that even the concept
      of a normative form is inapplicable to many signs.</p>

      <esp:sh>More on Sequences</esp:sh>

      <esp:ssh>Sequences are not encoded</esp:ssh>

      <p>Following the above principles, signs which are composed of
      sequences of multiple adjacent signs should not be encoded.  The
      surface form of sequences can be variable in the ordering,
      selection, and disposition of components, all of which are are
      treated as glyph variations and not as discrete characters.</p>

      <p>In Proto-Cuneiform writing sequences are not necessarily
      linear: because the manuscripts are organized in cases (or
      boxes), signs are routinely juxtaposed in clusters in which the
      components can be written above, below, or near each other as
      well as being beside each other in a line.</p>

      <esp:ssh>Opaque sequences are not encoded</esp:ssh>

      <p>In standard transliteration practice for Proto-Cuneiform some
      signs are given simple names which do not reflect their status
      as a sequence, e.g., LUGAL is actually a sequence of GAL₂ and
      LU₂, or LU₂ and GAL. We call these sequences "opaque sequences"
      and, like regular sequences, they are not encoded.</p>

      <esp:ssh>Reasons for Exceptions</esp:ssh>

      <p>Although sequences are not generally encoded, there are
      several reasons for making exceptions to this policy:</p>

      <dl>
	<dt>Reanalysis</dt>
	<dd>Proto-Cuneiform signs that are originally integral units
	may be reanalyzed into separate constituents. Where this is
	demonstrably the case, the original character is encoded and
	the reanalyzed sequence is considered a glyph variant.</dd>

	<!--
	<dt>Common Signs</dt>
	<dd>Some signs are allowed as exceptions because it would be
	counter-intuitive not to encode them as characters.</dd>
	-->
	
	<dt>Container Equivalency</dt>
	<dd>Some signs are allowed as exceptions because the
	juxtaposition of elements is the equivalent of a container
	(TIMES) relationship.</dd>
	
	<dt>Unencoded Constituents</dt>
	<dd>Some sequences contain constituents that are otherwise
	unattested; in this case the choice is either to encode a sign
	which may not be attested independently, or to encode the
	sequence.  In general the option adopted is to encode the
	sequence as a character.</dd>

	<dt>Analogy</dt>
	<dd>Some sequences are part of a group and would naturally be
	considered by users of the encoding to be analogous to each
	other. Where one or more members of a group fulfils either of
	the previous conditions for encoding as a character, PC25
	encodes the entire group as individual characters by analogy
	to avoid a possibly confusing mixture of encoded and unencoded
	group members.</dd>

      </dl>

      <esp:ssh>List of Exceptions</esp:ssh>

      <esp:sssh>Reanalysis</esp:sssh>

      <p>Two city-name signs, ADAB and ARARMA~a, have earlier forms
      which are distinct from their reanalysis to include an initial
      U₄ component.  Other city names may also have earlier integral
      forms but without further evidence they are not proposed for
      encoding as characters at this point.</p>

      <!--
      <esp:sh>Common Signs</esp:sh>

      <p>The signs LUGAL (GAL+LU) and LI (ŠE+ŠA) are encoded as
      characters as common sign exceptions.</p>
      -->
      
      <esp:sssh>Container Equivalency</esp:sssh>

      <p>The signs ASAR and AZ are the equivalent of containers.</p>
      
      <esp:sssh>Unencoded Constituents</esp:sssh>

      <p>The following exception signs contain unencoded consituents:
      <!--ENKUM (EZEN×ŠE),--> ME₃ (EŠDA-tenu), ŠAGINA (modified UŠ form with
      additional strokes, unclear with this is an UŠ or not), ZUBI~a
      (NA₂-nutillu).</p>
      
      <esp:sssh>Analogy: BAPPIR Group</esp:sssh>

      <p>The group of signs with the base BAPPIR has one member which
      is a container (BAPPIR~e) and the entire group is encoded by
      analogy.</p>

      <!--
      <esp:sh>Analogy: ŠELU</esp:sh>

      <p>Most combinations of ŠE plus another sign are encoded as
      characters (e.g., TU) so an exception is made for ŠELU.</p>
      -->
      
      <esp:sssh>Analogy: Sheep Group</esp:sssh>

      <p>The groups of signs with the base SILANITA, UDUNITA and UTUA
      represent various types (ages, genders) of sheep and since some
      of them have unencoded constituents the members of all groups
      are encoded as characters.</p>

      <esp:sssh>Analogy: UTUL Group</esp:sssh>

      <p>The UTUL group contains one member which includes an uncoded
      superposed reduplicated component (UTUL~c), so the entire group
      is encoded as characters.</p>
      
    </body>
  </html>
</esp:page>
