<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<esp:page xmlns:esp="http://oracc.org/ns/esp/1.0" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" xmlns:xh="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" xmlns:xpd="http://oracc.org/ns/xpd/1.0">
  <esp:name>Exceptions</esp:name>
  <esp:title>PC25: Sequence Exceptions</esp:title>
  <html>
    <head/>
    <body>
      <esp:h>Principle and Practice</esp:h>
      <p>In principle, sign list entries which are sequences of
      separate signs are not encoded in PC25. In practice, there are
      several reasons for making exceptions to this policy:</p>
      <dl>
        <dt>Reanalysis</dt>
        <dd>Proto-Cuneiform signs that are originally integral units
	may be reanalyzed into separate constituents. Where this is
	demonstrably the case, the original character is encoded and
	the reanalyzed sequence is considered a glyph variant.</dd>
        <dt>Common Signs</dt>
        <dd>Some signs are allowed as exceptions because it would be
	counter-intuitive not to encode them as characters.</dd>
        <dt>Container Equivalency</dt>
        <dd>Some signs are allowed as exceptions because the
	juxtaposition of elements is the equivalent of a container
	(TIMES) relationship.</dd>
        <dt>Unencoded Constituents</dt>
        <dd>Some sequences contain constituents that are otherwise
	unattested; in this case the choice is either to encode a sign
	which may not be attested independently, or to encode the
	sequence.  In general the option adopted is to encode the
	sequence as a character.</dd>
        <dt>Analogy</dt>
        <dd>Some sequences are part of a group and would naturally be
	considered by users of the encoding to be analogous to each
	other. Where one or more members of a group fulfils either of
	the previous conditions for encoding as a character, PC25
	encodes the entire group as individual characters by analogy
	to avoid a possibly confusing mixture of encoded and unencoded
	group members.</dd>
      </dl>
      <esp:h>List of Exceptions</esp:h>
      <esp:sh>Reanalysis</esp:sh>
      <p>Two city-name signs, ADAB and ARARMA~a, have earlier forms
      which are distinct from their reanalysis to include an initial
      U₄ component.  Other city names may also have earlier integral
      forms but without further evidence they are not proposed for
      encoding as characters at this point.</p>
      <esp:sh>Common Signs</esp:sh>
      <p>The signs LUGAL (GAL+LU) and LI (ŠE+ŠA) are encoded as
      characters as common sign exceptions.</p>
      <esp:sh>Container Equivalency</esp:sh>
      <p>The signs ASAR and AZ are the equivalent of containers.</p>
      <esp:sh>Unencoded Constituents</esp:sh>
      <p>The following exception signs contain unencoded consituents:
      ENKUM (EZEN×ŠE), ME₃ (EŠDA-tenu), ŠAGINA (modified UŠ form with
      additional strokes, unclear with this is an UŠ or not), ZUBI~a
      (NA₂-nutillu).</p>
      <esp:sh>Analogy: BAPPIR Group</esp:sh>
      <p>The group of signs with the base BAPPIR has one member which
      is a container (BAPPIR~e) and the entire group is encoded by
      analogy.</p>
      <esp:sh>Analogy: ŠELU</esp:sh>
      <p>Most combinations of ŠE plus another sign are encoded as
      characters (e.g., TU) so an exception is made for ŠELU.</p>
      <esp:sh>Analogy: Sheep Group</esp:sh>
      <p>The groups of signs with the base SILANITA, UDUNITA and UTUA
      represent various types (ages, genders) of sheep and since some
      of them have unencoded constituents the members of all groups
      are encoded as characters.</p>
      <esp:sh>Analogy: UTUL Group</esp:sh>
      <p>The UTUL group contains one member which includes an uncoded
      superposed reduplicated component (UTUL~c), so the entire group
      is encoded as characters.</p>
    </body>
  </html>
</esp:page>
