<?xml version="1.0"?>
<esp:page xmlns:esp="http://oracc.org/ns/esp/1.0" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" xmlns:xh="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" xmlns:sl="http://oracc.org/ns/sl/1.0"><esp:name>Abbreviations</esp:name><esp:title>Abbreviations</esp:title><html><head/><body><dl><dt>AP23</dt><dd><p>Anshuman Pandey's CDLI-NAME field as used in the proposal L2/23-190</p><p>https://www.unicode.org/L2/L2023/23190-proto-cuneiform.pdf</p></dd><dt>ATFU-S</dt><dd><p>ATFU sign name for PCSL sign</p><p>C. Lecompte and L. Verderame (ed.) Archaic Tablets and Fragments from Ur. (Nisaba 25). Messina, 2013.</p><p>Because the ATFU sign list is unnumbered we use @sys ATFU-S entries to catalogue ATFU
	113-126, Section VII, “Index of Signs”, which lists the signs occurring in the tablets published
	in Nisaba 25.  The signs are not numbered and are referenced by name.</p></dd><dt>ATFU-v</dt><dd><p>ATFU proposed Sumerian values.</p><p>See note to ATFU-S</p></dd><dt>ATU</dt><dd><p>Adam Falkenstein, "Archaische Texte aus Uruk" (ATU 1), Berlin 1936.</p><p>Signs in ATU 1 are referred to as, e.g., ATU001; texts in ATU are referred to as, e.g., ATU 1, 1.</p></dd><dt>BAU</dt><dd><p>E. Burrows, Archaic Texts (Ur Excavations Texts 2), London 1935.</p><p>BAU is aligned to AP designations; CDLI UET 2 transliterations do not always match these.
	For example, BAU104=IŠ~b1, BAU105=IŠ~b2 but UET 2 transliterations generally use IŠ~a for
	both forms. Alignments with CDLI-tc are sometimes approximate, e.g., BAU278=SILA₄~b;
	BAU311=AD~a.</p></dd><dt>CDLI-gh</dt><dd><p>CDLI-github sign list</p><p>Available at https://cdli-gh.github.io/proto-cuneiform_signs/.</p></dd><dt>CDLI-tc</dt><dd><p>CDLI text corpus--the CDLI transliterations of Uruk IV and Uruk III texts</p><p>This corpus is available at https://cdli.mpiwg-berlin.mpg.de/ or at http://oracc.org/pcsl.
	Transliteration conventions do not always match CDLI-gh.</p></dd><dt>CUSAS01</dt><dd><p>S.F. Monaco, The Cornell University Archaic Tablets (CUSAS 1), Bethesda, MD, 2007.</p><p>Additional signs on pages 15, “New Signs and Sign Variants” and 281, “New Signs and Variants”.</p></dd><dt>CUSAS21</dt><dd><p>S.F. Monaco, Archaic Bullae and Tablets in the Cornell University Collections (CUSAS 21), Bethesda, MD, 2014.</p><p>Additional signs on page 166, “New Signs and Variants”.</p></dd><dt>CUSAS31</dt><dd><p>S.F. Monaco, Archaic Cuneiform Tablets from Private Collections (CUSAS 31), Bethesda, MD, 2016.</p><p>Additional signs on page 203, “New Signs and Variants”.</p></dd><dt>DISAMB</dt><dd><p>INTERNAL</p></dd><dt>LLATU</dt><dd><p>Lexicalischen Listen der Archaischen Texte aus Uruk</p><p>Pp.177-327 in Robert K. Englund und Hans J. Nissen unter Mitarbeit von Peter Damerow,
	"Die Lexikalischen Listen der Archaischen Texte aus Uruk" (ATU 3), Berlin 1993.</p><p>The definitive edition of lexical texts from Uruk has its own sign index in which signs are
	often further differentiated compared to ZATU by adding lowercase letters. The signs are not
	numbered as a signlist but are listed alphabetically with references.</p></dd><dt>RKEZ</dt><dd><p>R.K.Englund, “Liste der zusätzlichen Zeichen der Text der 33. und 34. Kampagne” Pp. 347-351 in ZATU.</p></dd><dt>UNMKEY</dt><dd><p>INTERNAL</p></dd><dt>ZATU</dt><dd><p>M. W. Green und Hans J. Nissen, unter Mitarbeit von Peter Damerow und Robert K. Englund,
	"Zeichenliste der Archaischen Texte aus Uruk" (ATU 2), Berlin 1987.</p></dd></dl></body></html></esp:page>
