<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<esp:page xmlns:esp="http://oracc.org/ns/esp/1.0"
	  xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
	  xmlns:xh="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
	  xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <esp:name>Repertoire</esp:name>
  <esp:title>Repertoire</esp:title>
  <html>
    <head/>
    <body>

      <p>The complete unified list of the proposed PC25 repertoire is
      <esp:link url="/pcsl/pc25/pc25-tab.html">available here</esp:link>.</p>

      <p>The repertoire is created using the CDLI-PCSL text corpus and
      unified PCSL sign list as starting points.  Signs are removed
      from PCSL for the following reasons:</p>

      <ol>

	<li><span class="remfor">Corpus scope:</span>&#x20;
	<xi:include xml:base="." href="counts/no_corpus.cnt" parse="text"/>
	signs are first removed because they do not occur in the PC25
	subcorpus.  For a list of these signs see <esp:link
	url="/pcsl/pc25/no_corpus.html">Appendix 2</esp:link>.</li>

	<li><span class="remfor">Non-contrastive variants:</span>&#xa;
	XXX glyphs are not removed as such but do not enter into
	consideration because PC25 does not encode non-contrastive
	glyph variants.</li>
	
	<li><span class="remfor">Ineligible Numbers:</span>&#x20;
	<xi:include xml:base="." href="counts/no_number.cnt" parse="text"/>
	signs are removed because they are numbers that are either
	encoded already in the Archaic Cuneiform Numbers proposal
	(ACN) or because PC25 does not generally include numbers
	(exceptions include the N57 and U₄-time sequences). For a list
	of these signs, excluding those in ACN, see <esp:link
	url="/pcsl/pc25/no_numberxacn.html">Appendix 3</esp:link>.</li>

	<li><span class="remfor">Sequences:</span>&#x20;
	<xi:include xml:base="." href="counts/no_sequence.cnt" parse="text"/>
	signs are removed because they are sequences. PC25 makes no
	distinction between opaque sequences--those whose label hides
	the fact that the sign is a sequence--and simple sequences.
	PC25 does propose to encode several exceptional groups of
	sequences as described in the <esp:url
	page="pc25seqexc">Sequence Exceptions</esp:url> section.  A
	list of excluded sequences is given in <esp:link
	url="/pcsl/pc25/no_sequence.html">Appendix 4</esp:link>.</li>

	<li><span class="remfor">Broken signs:</span>&#x20;
	<xi:include xml:base="." href="counts/no_broken.cnt" parse="text"/>
	are removed because they are damaged and partially incomplete.
	A list of broken signs is given in <esp:link
	url="/pcsl/pc25/no_broken.html">Appendix 5</esp:link>.</li>

	<li><span class="remfor">Deleted signs:</span>&#x20;
	<xi:include xml:base="." href="counts/no_broken.cnt" parse="text"/>
	signs are deleted despited surviving the preceding conditions
	because they are duplicates.  A list of deleted signs is given
	in <esp:link url="/pcsl/pc25/no_broken.html">Appendix
	6</esp:link>.</li>
	
      </ol>
      
      <esp:h>Notes on individual classes of inclusions</esp:h>
      
      <esp:sh>Signs with non-contrastive variants</esp:sh>

      <p>The 190 signs which have non-contrastive variants, with the
      proposed reference glyph in initial position in the list, is
      <esp:link page="repncv">given here</esp:link>.</p>

      <esp:sh>Numbers</esp:sh>

      <p>Although PC25 is primarily focussed on ideograms, <esp:link
      page="repnum">some numbers, listed here</esp:link>, need to be
      encoded to support N(N57) sequences.  This is a class of
      additions to AP24, which omitted all numbers.</p>

      <esp:sh>City Names</esp:sh>

      <p>A list of the signs which represent city names and are
      assigned codepoints rather than being treated as sequences is
      <esp:link page="repcity">given here</esp:link>.</p>
      
    </body>
  </html>
</esp:page>
