<esp:page xmlns:esp="http://oracc.org/ns/esp/1.0"
	  xmlns:tex="http://oracc.org/ns/tex/1.0"
	  xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">

<h1>The Archaic Period in Mesopotamia</h1>

<tex:text>
  <tex:latex>
    \begin{figure}[h]
    \centering
    \captionsetup{width=.75\linewidth}
    \includegraphics[scale=.4]{images/benati-map.png}
    \caption{Map of southern
  Iraq showing canal networks and key settlements of the late fourth
  and early third millennia BCE (from \cite{Benati2015})}
    \end{figure}
  </tex:latex>
  <tex:plain>
  \xgraphicsfigure{images/benati-map.png}{500}{5in}{Map of southern
  Iraq showing canal networks and key settlements of the late fourth
  and early third millennia BCE (after Benati,
  https://cdli.earth/articles/cdlj/2015-2)}</tex:plain></tex:text>

<p>Proto-cuneiform script was invented in southern Iraq in the second
half of the third millennium BCE and used until the early part of the
second millennium BCE, approximately 3500-2900 BCE, generally known as
the Archaic Period. This period was extensively described and
discussed, with special reference to texts and writing, by the late
Robert K. Englund in his magisterial book-within-a-book “Texts from
the Late Uruk Period" \cite{Englund1998}.  The following sketch is
based largely on Englund's discussion to which the reader is referred
for a detailed account.</p>

<h2>Birth of Cities</h2>

<p>The flourishing of urbanization in southern Mesopotamia during the
fourth millennium BCE gave rise to several major centres of which the
best known and most excavated is that of Uruk.  Major institutional
buildings, new artistic forms illustrating the importance of the ruler
and the relationship of the ruler and the gods, and the invention of
writing are all features of socio-political developments in the first
cities.</p>

<p>Networks of canals connected important centres and the distribution
of material culture and writing show that the world of the Archaic
Uruk period was characterized by significant interaction between
communities, not only within southern Mesopotamia but in ``Uruk
enclaves'' in the Susiana plain of modern Iran and in modern Syria and
Türkiye where Uruk architecture, visual arts, and administrative
systems indicate the presence of Uruk colonies for trading or resource
extraction \cite{Algaze1993,Algaze2005}.</p>

<h2>History</h2>

<tex:text>
  <tex:latex>
    \begin{figure}[h]
    \centering
    \captionsetup{width=.75\linewidth}
    \includegraphics[scale=.49]{images/obo-chrono.png}
    \caption{Chronological overview of early Mesopotamia from \cite[23]{Englund1998}}
    \end{figure}
  </tex:latex>
  <tex:plain>
    \xgraphicsfigure{images/obo-chrono.png}{500}{3in}{Chronological overview of early Mesopotamia from Englund p.23.}</tex:plain></tex:text>

<p>We cannot write a political history of the late fourth millennium,
and the lack of archaeological context for key Uruk period textual
finds means that we must resort to dating the tablet finds by relative
palegraphical criteria rather than by documented archaeological
findspots.</p>

<p>The sporadic nature of both archaeological excavations and text
corpora is another impediment to a continuous history of these early
periods, as Algaze notes in his excellent synthesis of the Uruk period
primarily from the archaeological perspective \cite{Algaze2013}.
Algaze reviews the surface survey data, excavations, and (in less
detail) the textual finds from all parts of the Uruk world and
presents a coherent picture of a cyclical efflorescence and decline of
major cities in the south each with their own networks of smaller
settlements in a hierarchy up to four levels deep.  In addition, as
mentioned above, there is extensive evidence of relatively far-flung
colonial outcroppings. Considering the extent of these hundreds of
settlements active, albeit often episodically or intermittently, over
five to six hundred years, the text-corpus of less than 7000 documents
from a handful of sites presumably only represents a small subset of
the ancient textual material generated and, in some cases, still
awaiting excavation.</p>

<h2>Major Text Corpora</h2>

<p>Figure 2 provides a schematic overview of the sequence of major
text finds in the `Writing Phase' column. The entry `Clay bullae and
numerical tablets' in the Writing Phase column is the equivalent of
the periodic classification Uruk V.  Only small groups of texts are
omitted from the subsequent Late Uruk (Uruk IV and Uruk III) into the
Jemdet Nasr period (examples include Uqair, Larsa).  For ED I--II we
have the ED I--II Ur texts \cite{Burrows1935,LecompteVerderame2013}; a few
tablets from Uruk which are later than archaic \cite{Green1982}; and
some tablets from Fara that are earlier than ED IIIa
\cite{Krebernik2014}.  Then the record is silent until Fara
(Šuruppak) \cite{Krebernik1998}.</p>

<p>The largest and most important group of archaic texts was excavated
in the city of Uruk. The tablets were found in secondary context,
meaning that the relative dating of tablets to Uruk IV or the later
Uruk III is not based on stratigraphy but on formal and palaeographic
features \cite[318-323]{Nissen1986}.  About 100 tablets and bullae are
assigned to the Uruk V period which precedes Uruk IV by an uncertain
amount of time.  The Uruk period text corpus is described in more
detail in section \ref{texts}.</p>

<p>As Englund demonstrates the archaic text corpus reflects
organized agriculture, animal husbandry, and other production. The
documents evidence social hierarchy and specialization, including the
birth of scribal culture in early Mesopotamia.</p>

<h3>Administrative Texts</h3>

<tex:text>
  <tex:latex>
    \begin{figure}[!htb]
    \centering
    \captionsetup{width=.75\linewidth}
    \includegraphics[scale=.3]{images/depc-P005340.png}
    \caption{Beer dossier account of Kushim
    \cite{P005340} with copy and explanation by Bob Englund and Peter Damerow
    \cite[37]{DamerowEnglund1993}.}
    \end{figure}
  </tex:latex>
</tex:text>

<p>The bulk of the archaic tablets are administrative documents. They
exhibit varying degrees of complexity from simple tags or
one-transaction memos to multi-transactional summaries with a
relatively complex organization of cases as indicated in figures 3 and
4.</p>

<p>A number of studies have analysed subgroups of the administrative
texts, with the result that the content and methodologies of the
archaic accounting records are well understood.</p>

<p>An early example is Margeret Green's work on animal husbandry
\cite{Green1980}, which is complemented by Englund's work on dairy
metrology \cite{Englund1991} and production \cite{Englund1995} and the
herding of pigs and other animals \cite{Englund1995-1}, as well as
J. Cale Johnson's essays on butchering \cite{Johnson2016} and ritual
meat distribution \cite{Johnson2019}.</p>

<p>Other studies have examined grain accounting \cite{Englund2001} and
time designations \cite[121-127]{Englund1998}.  One of the earliest
dossiers of activity of a named individual, Kušim the brewer, is
studied by Peter Damerow and Bob Englund in
\cite{DamerowEnglund1993}.</p>

<p>In another important contribution with far-reaching implications,
Englund also forged new paths in the identification of personal names
of labourers--probably captured slaves--in a small group of tablets
from Uruk and Umma \cite{Englund2009}.</p>

<tex:text>
  <tex:latex>
    \begin{figure}[!htb]
    \centering
    \captionsetup{width=.75\linewidth}
    \includegraphics[scale=.33]{images/P005252.png}
    \caption{The complex summation MSVO 1, 185 with Englund's analysis.}
    \end{figure}
  </tex:latex>
  <tex:plain>
    \xgraphicsfigure{images/P005252.png}{425}{5in}{The complex summation MSVO 1, 185 with Englund's analysis.}</tex:plain></tex:text>

<tex:text>
  <tex:latex>
    \begin{figure}[!htb]
    \centering
    \captionsetup{width=.75\linewidth}
    \includegraphics[scale=.6]{images/depc-P003500.png}
    \caption{Personnel list
    \cite{P003500} with Englund's copy and transliteration
    \cite[13]{Englund2009}.  The expressions AL, EN~a TUR, 1(N57)×U4
    TUR, BULUG₃, U₂~a A and ŠU are probably age qualifications of
    individuals.}
    \end{figure}
  </tex:latex>
</tex:text>

<h3>Lexical Lists</h3>

<tex:text>
  <tex:latex>
    \begin{figure}[!htb]
    \centering
    \captionsetup{width=.75\linewidth}
    \includegraphics[scale=.4]{images/lex.png}
    \caption{Sample lexical tablets: Professions \cite{P000006}, \cite{P000011}; Archaic Vocabulary \cite{P000025}}
    \end{figure}
  </tex:latex>
  <tex:plain>
    \xgraphicsfigure{images/lex.png}{250}{5in}{Sample lexical tablets: P000006, P000011, P000025.}
  </tex:plain>
</tex:text>

<p>The other important--but numerically far smaller--group of texts
are the word lists that Assyriologists generally refer to as `Lexical
Texts'.  These appear in the earlist phases of writing and are
especially well evidenced in Uruk III texts.</p>

<p>The best attested of these is the list of professions and
occupations usually called `Archaic Lu A', `Professions', or some
combination thereof.  More than 60 fragments of this list have been
identified, from which an almost complete composite text can be
reconstructed.  The creation of a composite text is a common
disciplinary practice with lexical lists which are attested mostly in
small fragments containing only a few lines of the text: combining
these overlapping fragments, which exhibit a generally if not
perfectly consistent order and selection of lines, results in a
reconstructed text which facilitates working with the data.</p>

<p>The range of archaic lexical texts is modest but invaluable.  The
lists are primarily thematic, covering Vessels and Garments (the
second-best attested list after Professions); Metals; Wood; Cattle;
Officials; Cities; Geography; Fish; Food; Birds; and Plants.  There
are also some word lists which are not strictly thematic.  An
excellent overview is given by Niek Veldhuis in
\cite[27-59]{Veldhuis2014}.</p>

<tex:text>
  <tex:latex>
    \begin{figure}[!htb]
    \captionsetup{width=.75\linewidth}
    \includegraphics[scale=.6]{images/obo-lucompo.png}
    \centering
    \caption{Englund's composite of the professions/occupations list, Lu. Shaded areas are entries that cannot be fully reconstructed from the extant manuscripts.}
    \end{figure}
  </tex:latex>
  <tex:plain>
\graphicsfigure{images/obo-lucompo.png}{275}{3in}{Englund's composite of the professions/occupations list, Lu. Shaded areas are entries that cannot be fully reconstructed from the extant manuscripts.}  </tex:plain>
</tex:text>

<p>Importantly, some of the archaic lexical lists continue into
Early Dynastic, where tablets from Fara and Abu Ṣalabīkh
write the same content but in contemporary cuneiform---see
\cite{LecompteDiss,Wagensonner2016,} with previous literature.</p>

<h2>Writing</h2>

<h3>Technology, Technique, Phases</h3>

<tex:latex>
  \begin{wrapfigure}[10]{r}{0.3333\textwidth}
  \centering
  \kern-10pt
  \includegraphics[width=0.3\textwidth]{images/nissen-WA-tech.png}
  \caption{Styli and sign development from \cite[320]{Nissen1986}}
  \end{wrapfigure}
</tex:latex>

<p>Proto-Cuneiform tablets are made of refined and formed clay, which
was inscribed when still slightly moist, establishing a practice that
continued for millennia to come \cite{Taylor2011}.  The earliest
tablets were inscribed with a pointed instrument--likely a sharpened
reed--with circular indentations made with a round tool, presumably
the other end of the stylus. The pointed tool was replaced with a
triangular-ended stylus which was impressed into, and in some cases
then dragged lightly across, the surface of the clay to produce the
characteristic triangular indentations with a deep head and a shallow
tail that give rise to the term `cuneiform'
\cite{Green1981,Nissen1986}.</p>

<tex:latex>
  \begin{figure}[h]
  \centering
  \includegraphics[scale=3]{images/obo-p69-cropped.png}
  \caption{Englund's overview of Uruk IV/Uruk III sign forms.}
  \end{figure}
</tex:latex>

<p>The precise analysis of writing phases in the Uruk texts is
hampered by the lack of tablet finds in primary archaeological context
\cite[318-323]{Nissen1986}. The general assumption is that earlier
sign forms are more curved; have a greater variety of angles; or are
drawn with a pointed stylus rather than being constructed of cuneiform
strokes.  Englund's discussion of this is accomplished with a figure
which is unfortunately absent from the PDF of the book; his Figure 22
is reproduced here \cite[69]{Englund1998}.</p>

<!--
<tex:latex>
  \begin{figure}[h]
  \centering
  \captionsetup{width=.75\linewidth}
  \end{figure}
</tex:latex>
-->

<h3>Orientation and Disposition</h3>

<tex:text>
    <tex:latex>
      \begin{figure}[!htb]
      \centering
      \captionsetup{width=.75\linewidth}
      \includegraphics[scale=.75]{images/obo-diplo.png}
      \caption{Sample tablet organizations; the CDLI transliterations utilize dotted line numbers to address cases of the form 1a.b2 etc.}
      \end{figure}
  </tex:latex>
  <tex:plain>
    \xgraphicsfigure{images/obo-diplo.png}{400}{3in}{Sample tablet organizations; the CDLI transliterations utilize dotted line numbers to address cases of the form 1a.b2 etc.}</tex:plain></tex:text>

<p>One longstanding point of discussion in the study of
Proto-Cuneiform and its descendants is the orientation of the script,
a discussion rooted in the fact that the later cuneiform versions of
signs as normally represented in hand copies and published images are
rotated 90 degrees from the expected natural orientation of their
pictographic forebears.  Thus the sign SAG, head, with forms {\pcseq
𒦘}, {\pcseq 󲅨}, {\pcseq 󲅩} approximately matches the cuneiform <span
class="oraccnoto">𒊕</span>. A more naturalistic rendering of SAG,
however, would be \rotatebox[origin=c]{270}{\pcseq 󲅨}, and this
orientation is preferred in some recent literature, e.g.,
\cite{Selz2025}.  In this proposal we follow conventional disciplinary
practice as adopted in the standard corpus publications of
Proto-Cuneiform and the CDLI.</p>

<p>The spatial division of Proto-Cuneiform administrative and lexical
tablets into cases which are often quite narrow gives rise to an
important feature of the disposition of combinations of signs, which
may be placed beside, above, or otherwise near each other as space
permits, and may be written in varying order depending partly on the
space available in the box into which the signs have to fit.  This has
an important impact on the determination and treatment of sequences,
as explained in \ref{sequences}.</p>

<h3>Semantics</h3>

<p>The language of the archaic corpus is uncertain: many would accept
that it is Sumerian, but for Englund and others this remains
stubbornly unprovable (see recently \cite{Keetman2020}.  Despite this,
continuities between PC and later cuneiform, contextual inferences
drawn from counting and measuring systems, and the similarity of some
signs to the objects they picture all combine to allow the general
sense of many signs or groups of signs to be divined.  Two of
Englund's figures are chosen here to illustrate this point, but the
entirety of “Texts from the Late Uruk Period" is in a sense his
demonstration that the archaic corpus--contrary to what some might
think--is increasingly well understood.</p>

<tex:latex>
  \begin{figure}[h]
  \centering
  \begin{minipage}{0.475\textwidth}
  \includegraphics[scale=.25]{images/obo-ovo.png}
  \caption{Signs for ovi-caprids, after Englund.}
  \end{minipage}
  \begin{minipage}{0.475\textwidth}
  \includegraphics[scale=.3]{images/obo-dairy.png}
  \caption{Signs for dairy products, after Englund.}
  \end{minipage}
  \end{figure}
</tex:latex>

</esp:page>
