<esp:page xmlns:esp="http://oracc.org/ns/esp/1.0"
	  xmlns:tex="http://oracc.org/ns/tex/1.0"
	  xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">

<h1>The Archaic Period in Mesopotamia</h1>

<p>Proto-cuneiform script was invented in the second half of the third
millennium BCE and used until the early part of the second millennium
BCE, approximately 3500-2900 BCE, generally known as the Archaic
Period. This period was extensively described and discussed, with
special reference to texts and writing, by the late Robert K. Englund
in his magisterial book-within-a-book "Texts from the Late Uruk
Period", pages 1-233 in J. Bauer, R.K. Englund and M. Krebernik,
<i>Mesopotamien: Spaturuk-Zeit und Frhudynastische Zeit</i> (Orbis
Biblicus et Orientalis 160/1). Gottingen, 1998, available as an open
access download at https://www.zora.uzh.ch/id/eprint/151545/.  The
following sketch is based on Englund's discussion to which the reader
is referred for a detailed account.</p>

<h2>Birth of Cities</h2>

<p>The flourishing of urbanization in southern Mesopotamia during the
fourth millennium BCE gave rise to several major centres of which the
best known and most excavated is that of Uruk.  Major institutional
buildings, new artistic forms illustrating the importance of the ruler
and the relationship of the ruler and the gods, and the invention of
writing are all features of socio-political developments in the first
cities.</p>

<p>Networks of canals connected important centres and the distribution
of material culture and writing show that the world of the Archaic
Uruk period was characterized by significant interaction between
communities.</p>

<tex:text>
  <tex:latex>
    \begin{figure}[h]
    \centering
    \includegraphics[width=.5\linewidth,scale=.3]{images/benati-map.png}\caption{Map of southern
  Iraq showing canal networks and key settlements of the late fourth
  and early third millennia BCE (after Benati,
  https://cdli.earth/articles/cdlj/2015-2)}
    \end{figure}
  </tex:latex>
  <tex:plain>
  \xgraphicsfigure{images/benati-map.png}{500}{5in}{Map of southern
  Iraq showing canal networks and key settlements of the late fourth
  and early third millennia BCE (after Benati,
  https://cdli.earth/articles/cdlj/2015-2)}</tex:plain></tex:text>

<h2>History</h2>

<p>We cannot write a political history of the late fourth millennium,
and the lack of archaeological context for key Uruk period finds means
that we must resort to dating the tablet finds by relative
palegraphical criteria rather than by documented archaeological
findspots.</p>

<p>As Englund demonstrates, however, archaic administrative texts
reflect organized agriculture, animal husbandry, and other
production. The documents evidence social hierarchy and specialization
and some texts can be understood as inventories of labourers, possibly
slaves captured in military operations.</p>

<p>The sporadic nature of both archaeological excavations and text
corpora is another impediment to a continuous history of these early
periods.  Figure 2 provides a schematic overview of the sequence of
major text finds in the 'Writing Phase' column. The entry 'Clay bullae
and numerical tablets' in the Writing Phase column is the equivalent
of the periodic classification Uruk V.  Only small groups of texts are
omitted from the subsequent Late Uruk (Uruk IV and Uruk III) into the
Jemdet Nasr period (examples include Uqair, Larsa).  For ED I--II we
have only the ED I-II Ur texts and a few dozen tablets from Uruk which
are later than archaic.  Then the record is silent until Fara
(Šuruppak).</p>

<tex:text>
  <tex:latex>
    \begin{figure}[h]
    \centering
    \includegraphics[width=.5\linewidth,scale=.3]{images/obo-chrono.png}
    \caption{Chronological overview of early Mesopotamia from Englund p.23.}
    \end{figure}
  </tex:latex>
  <tex:plain>
    \xgraphicsfigure{images/obo-chrono.png}{500}{3in}{Chronological overview of early Mesopotamia from Englund p.23.}</tex:plain></tex:text>

<h2>Major Text Corpora</h2>

<p>The largest and most important group of archaic texts was excavated
in the city of Uruk. The tablets were found in secondary context,
meaning that the relative dating of tablets to Uruk IV or the later
Uruk III is not based on stratigraphy but on formal and palaeographic
features.  About 100 tablets and bullae are assigned to the Uruk V
period which precedes Uruk IV by an uncertain amount of time.</p>

<h3>Administrative Texts</h3>

<p>The bulk of the archaic tablets are administrative documents. They
exhibit varying degrees of complexity from simple tags or
one-transaction memos to multi-transactional summaries with a
relatively complex organization of cases as indicated in figures 3 and 4.</p>

<tex:text>
    <tex:latex>
      \begin{figure}[h]
      \centering
      \includegraphics[width=.5\linewidth,scale=.3]{images/obo-diplo.png}
      \caption{Sample tablet organizations; the CDLI transliterations utilize dotted line numbers to address cases of the form 1a.b2 etc.}
      \end{figure}
  </tex:latex>
  <tex:plain>
    \xgraphicsfigure{images/obo-diplo.png}{400}{3in}{Sample tablet organizations; the CDLI transliterations utilize dotted line numbers to address cases of the form 1a.b2 etc.}</tex:plain></tex:text>

<p>This form of spatial division of the tablets into cases which are
often quite narrow gives rise to an important feature of the writing
of combinations of signs, which may be place beside, above, or
otherwise near each other as space permits, and may be written in
varying order depending partly on the space available in the box into
which the signs have to fit.</p>

<tex:text>
  <tex:latex>
    \begin{figure}[h]
    \includegraphics[width=.5\linewidth,scale=.3]{images/P005252.png}
    \caption{The complex summation MSVO 1, 185 with Englund's analysis.}
    \end{figure}
  </tex:latex>
  <tex:plain>
    \xgraphicsfigure{images/P005252.png}{425}{5in}{The complex summation MSVO 1, 185 with Englund's analysis.}</tex:plain></tex:text>

<h3>Lexical Lists</h3>

<p>The other important--but numerically far fewer--group of texts are
the word lists that Assyriologists generally refer to as 'Lexical
Texts'.  These appear in the earlist phases of writing and are
especially well evidenced in Uruk III texts. Importantly, many of
these lexical lists continue into the Early Dynastic period, where
manuscripts from Fara and Abu Ṣalabīkh write the same content but in
contemporary cuneiform.  This provides the best evidence for the
alignment of PC and SAC, but an account of these alignments is beyond
the scope of Unicode.</p>

<tex:text>
  <tex:latex>
    \begin{figure}[h]
    \includegraphics[width=.5\linewidth,scale=.3]{images/obo-lucompo.png}
    \centering
    \caption{Englund's composite of the professions/occupations list, Lu. Shaded areas are entries that cannot be fully reconstructed from the extant manuscripts.}
    \end{figure}
  </tex:latex>
  <tex:plain>
\graphicsfigure{images/obo-lucompo.png}{275}{3in}{Englund's composite of the professions/occupations list, Lu. Shaded areas are entries that cannot be fully reconstructed from the extant manuscripts.}  </tex:plain>
</tex:text>

<p>The disciplinary practice with lexical lists, which are attested
mostly in small fragments containing only a few lines of the text, is
to create composites which allow for an overview of the list and in
which each individual entry is evidenced by one or more manuscripts. A
sample composite is given in the figure above, and examples of lexical
tablets are below.</p>

<tex:text>
  <tex:latex>
    \begin{figure}[h]
    \centering
    \includegraphics[width=.5\linewidth,scale=.3]{images/lex.png}
    \caption{Sample lexical tablets: P000006, P000011, P000025}
    \end{figure}
  </tex:latex>
  <tex:plain>
    \xgraphicsfigure{images/lex.png}{250}{5in}{Sample lexical tablets: P000006, P000011, P000025.}
  </tex:plain>
</tex:text>

<h2>Writing Phases</h2>

<p>The precise analysis of writing phases in the Uruk texts is
hampered by the lack of tablet finds in primary archaeological
context. The general assumption is that earlier sign forms are more
curved; have a greater variety of angles; or are drawn with a pointed
stylus rather than being constructed of cuneiform strokes.  Englund's
discussion of this is accompanied by a figure which is unfortunately
absent from the PDF of the book; his Figure 22 is reproduced here.</p>

<tex:text>
  <tex:latex>
    \begin{figure}[p]
    \centering
    \includegraphics[width=.5\linewidth,scale=4]{images/obo-p69.png}
    \caption{Englund's overview of Uruk IV/Uruk III sign forms.}
    \end{figure}
  </tex:latex>
  <tex:plain>
    \xgraphicsfigure{images/obo-p69.png}{3000}{3in}{Englund's overview of Uruk IV/Uruk III sign forms.}</tex:plain></tex:text>

<h2>Vocabulary</h2>

<p>The language of the archaic corpus is uncertain: many would accept
that it is Sumerian, but for Englund and others this remains
stubbornly unprovable.  Despite this, continuities between PC and
later cuneiform, contextual inferences drawn from counting and
measuring systems, and the similarity of some signs to the objects
they picture all combine to allow the general sense of many signs or
groups of signs to be divined.  Two of Englund's figures are chosen
here to illustrate this point, but the entirety of "Texts from the
Late Uruk Period" is in a sense his demonstration that the archaic
corpus--contrary to what some might think--is increasingly well
understood.</p>

<tex:text>
  <tex:latex>
    \begin{figure}[h]
    \centering
    \includegraphics[width=.5\linewidth,scale=.3]{images/obo-ovo.png}
    \caption{Signs for ovi-caprids, after Englund.}
    \end{figure}
  </tex:latex>
  <tex:plain>
\xgraphicsfigure{images/obo-ovo.png}{300}{3in}{Signs for ovi-caprids, after Englund.}</tex:plain></tex:text>

<tex:text>
    <tex:latex>
    \begin{figure}[h]
    \centering
    \includegraphics[width=.5\linewidth,scale=.3]{images/obo-dairy.png}
    \caption{Signs for dairy products, after Englund.}
    \end{figure}
  </tex:latex>
  <tex:plain>
\xgraphicsfigure{images/obo-dairy.png}{300}{3in}{Signs for dairy products, after Englund.}</tex:plain></tex:text>

</esp:page>
