<tex:driver
    xmlns:tex="http://oracc.org/ns/tex/1.0"
    xmlns:xh="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
    xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
    xmlns:xix="http://www.w3.org/2001/XIncludeNot"
    class="sub"
    >

  <tex:text>\section*{Appendices}</tex:text>

  <tex:text>\addcontentsline{toc}{section}{Appendices}</tex:text>
    
  <xh:p>Here we provide supporting documentation which exposes as much as
  possible of the decision-making processes and outcomes that are
  associated with the proposal.</xh:p>

  <xh:dl>
    
    <xh:dt>PCSL</xh:dt>

    <xh:dd>Appendix A gives the Proto-Cuneiform Sign List
    (http://oracc.org/pcsl) is condensed into a table which gives
    information on the entire PC signiary.  The corpus instances are
    represented by distributional summaries; alignment with ZATU is
    provided in the main character box, and the published per-volume
    sign lists are represented in their own columns.</xh:dd>

    <xh:dt>Deferred Characters</xh:dt>

    <xh:dd>Appendix B lists all of the characters that are not encoded
    because they occur only in unpublished texts.</xh:dd>

    <xh:dt>Excluded Characters</xh:dt>

    <xh:dd>Appendices C to I give tables of characters according to the
    rationale for their exclusion.</xh:dd>

    <xh:dt>Sequences</xh:dt>

    <xh:dd>Various relevant data about sequences are in Appendix J to L.</xh:dd>

    <xh:dt>Fonts</xh:dt>

    <xh:dd>A brief description of the fonts provided with the proposal is
    given in Appendix M.</xh:dd>

  </xh:dl>

  <tex:appendix>PCSL Table</tex:appendix>
  
  <xh:p>The PCSL Table condenses the Proto-Cuneiform Sign List into a
  convenient overview of the entire Proto-Cuneiform repertoire and its
  various data sources.  The contents of the columns are as follows:</xh:p>

  <xh:dl>
    <xh:dt>PCSL</xh:dt>
    <xh:dd><xh:p>The core PCSL data: the sign name and category tag are at the
    top of the case; the distribution, Oracc ID (OID) and ZATU number,
    if any, are at the bottom of the case. If the sign is proposed for
    encoding in PC25, the hex codepoint and reference glyph are given
    in the middle of the case.</xh:p>
    <xh:p>The tag codes are as follows:
    ACN=Archaic Cuneiform Numbers; 
    DEL=delete;
    EDI=ED I/II; 
    NOT=not encoded;
    NUM=number;
    OOR=out-of-range number;
    OOR5=out-of-range Uruk V number;
    PC25-bk=PC25-eligible but broken so no codepoint;
    PC25-sq=PC25-eligible but sequene so no codepoint;
    PC25=PC25 encoded;
    Pelm=planned for Proto-Elamite;
    UNP=occurs in unpublished texts only;
    ZERO=zero occurrences.
 </xh:p>
    <xh:p>CDLI names either from print sources or in the CDLI-gh name
    list that have been adapted to PCSL conventions appear in this
    block with the prefix <xh:code>CDLI:</xh:code>.</xh:p>
    <xh:p>CDLI names used in the transliterated corpus which are
    handled using aliases in the validation data appear in this block
    with the prefix <xh:code>AKA:</xh:code>.</xh:p>
    </xh:dd>
    <xh:dt>FONT</xh:dt>
    <xh:dd>The glyphs as given in PCSL.ttf, with their codepoints.
    Glyphs coloured blue are not included in the CDLI-gh
    collection. Subscript numbers before glyphs indicate the CVNN code
    for the variant, i.e., <xh:code>₁ = .cv01</xh:code></xh:dd>
    <xh:dt>CDLI</xh:dt>
    <xh:dd>The original CDLI-gh image, scaled from a 600dpi image set
    downloaded from the CDLI website in 2016.</xh:dd>
    <xh:dt>ATU3, ATU5, MSVO1, MSCO4, CUSAS</xh:dt>
    <xh:dd>Glyphs as given in the sign lists of the relevant text
    editions, but drawn from the PCSL font.  Glyphs in red differ in
    naming from CDLI-gh; <xh:code>(o)</xh:code> means that the instance has
    no variant code; <xh:code>(a), (b)</xh:code>, etc., means that the
    instance has the given variant code.</xh:dd>
  </xh:dl>

  <tex:text>\bigskip&#xa;&#xa;</tex:text>
  
  <xi:include href="../m/pcsl-tab.html"/>

  <tex:appendix>ZATU-PCSL Concordance</tex:appendix>

  <xi:include href="../m/zatu.html"/>
  
  <tex:appendix>Index of Alternate CDLI Sign Names</tex:appendix>

  <xh:p>This index covers two kinds of differences between CDLI names
  and PCSL names (ignoring the differences that result from
  re-encoding the CDLI names in Unicode rather than as ASCII).</xh:p>

  <xh:p>Changes made to the CDLI names are indicated with a
  greater-than (becomes) symbol, <xh:code>&gt;</xh:code>. These are CDLI
  names either in print or in the CDLI-gh name list that have been
  adapted to PCSL conventions.  These appear in the PCSL table in the
  main sign block with the prefix <xh:code>CDLI:</xh:code>.</xh:p>

  <xh:p>CDLI names used in the transliterated corpus have not
  generally been normalized to PCSL forms.  These are handled using
  aliases in the validation data, which appear in the PCSL table in
  the main block with the prefix <xh:code>AKA:</xh:code>.  Aliases in this
  index are indicated with the equals sign, <xh:code>=</xh:code>.</xh:p>

  <xi:include href="../m/aka-cdiff.xml"/>
  
  <tex:appendix>PCSL Non-PC25</tex:appendix>

  <xh:p>This table gives every text in the PC corpus that contains one
  or more unencoded signs, along with a list in the `Missing' column
  of the specific signs which are not included in the proposed PC25
  encoding.</xh:p>
  
  <tex:text>\bigskip&#xa;&#xa;</tex:text>

  <xi:include href="../m/notcov.html"/>  

  <tex:appendix>PC25 Not Encoded: Broken</tex:appendix>

  <xh:p>This table gives signs which are not encoded because they only
  occur in instances which are incomplete.</xh:p>
  
  <tex:text>\bigskip&#xa;&#xa;</tex:text>
  
  <xi:include href="../m/no_broken.html"/>

  <!--
  <tex:appendix>PC25 Not Encoded: Uruk V not in Sub-corpus</tex:appendix>

  <xh:p>This table gives signs excluded because they only occur in Uruk V.</xh:p>
  
  <tex:text>\bigskip&#xa;&#xa;</tex:text>
  
  <xi:include href="../m/no_uruk5.html"/>
  -->

  <tex:appendix>PC25 Not Encoded: Uruk IV/III not in Sub-corpus</tex:appendix>

  <xh:p>This table gives signs which do occur in Uruk IV and III but
  do not occur within the restricted PC25 corpus; this set is largely
  the same as that in Appendix B.</xh:p>
  
  <tex:text>\bigskip&#xa;&#xa;</tex:text>
  
  <xi:include href="../m/no_corpus.html"/>
  
  <tex:appendix>PC25 Not Encoded: ED I-II not in Sub-corpus</tex:appendix>

  <xh:p>This table gives signs excluded because they only occur in ED I--II</xh:p>

  <tex:text>\bigskip&#xa;&#xa;</tex:text>
  
  <xi:include href="../m/no_edi.html"/>
  
  <tex:appendix>PC25 Not Encoded: Delete</tex:appendix>

  <xh:p>This table gives signs which occur in CDLI-gh but have been
  deleted from the CDLI-tc.</xh:p>
  
  <tex:text>\bigskip&#xa;&#xa;</tex:text>
  
  <xi:include href="../m/no_delete.html"/>
  
  <tex:appendix>PC25 Not Encoded: Number (non-ACN)</tex:appendix>

  <xh:p>This table gives numbers which are neither in Archaic
  Cuneiform Numbers or in PC25.  Some of these may be candidates for
  future encoding.  The abbreviation `OOR' indicates numbers which are
  Out Of Range with regard to their respective system.  `OOR5'
  indicates an Out Of Range number occurring in Uruk V texts. The tag
  `Pelm' indicates numbers which are likely to be encoded as
  Proto-Elamite.</xh:p>
  
  <tex:text>\bigskip&#xa;&#xa;</tex:text>
  
  <xi:include href="../m/no_numberxacn.html"/>

  <!--
  <tex:appendix>PC25 Not Encoded: Sequence</tex:appendix>

  <xh:p>This table gives sequences which are not encoded.</xh:p>

  <tex:text>\bigskip&#xa;&#xa;</tex:text>
  
  <xi:include href="../m/no_sequence.html"/>

  -->
  
  <tex:appendix>PC25 Sequences Encoded as Exceptions</tex:appendix>

  <xh:p>This table gives sequences which are encoded because they have
  some exceptional characteristic against the principle that sequences
  are not encoded.</xh:p>
  
  <xh:h2>Reasons for Exceptions</xh:h2>

  <xh:h3>Reanalysis</xh:h3>

  <xh:p>Two city-name signs, ADAB and ARARMA~a, have earlier forms
  which are distinct from their reanalysis to include an initial
  U₄ component.  Other city names may also have earlier integral
  forms but without further evidence they are not proposed for
  encoding as characters at this point.</xh:p>

  <xh:h3>Container Equivalency</xh:h3>

  <xh:p>The signs ASAR and AZ are the equivalent of containers.</xh:p>
  
  <xh:h3>Unencoded Constituents</xh:h3>

  <xh:p>The following exception signs contain unencoded consituents:
  ME₃ (EŠDA-tenu), ŠAGINA (modified UŠ form with additional strokes,
  unclear with this is an UŠ or not), ZUBI~a (NA₂-nutillu).</xh:p>
  
  <xh:h3>Analogy: BAPPIR Group</xh:h3>

  <xh:p>The group of signs with the base BAPPIR has one member which
  is a container (BAPPIR~e) and the entire group is encoded by
  analogy.</xh:p>
      
  <xh:h3>Analogy: Sheep Group</xh:h3>

  <xh:p>The groups of signs with the base SILANITA, UDUNITA and UTUA
  represent various types (ages, genders) of sheep and since some
  of them have unencoded constituents the members of all groups
  are encoded as characters.</xh:p>

  <xh:h3>Analogy: UTUL Group</xh:h3>

  <xh:p>The UTUL group contains one member which includes an uncoded
  superposed reduplicated component (UTUL~c), so the entire group
  is encoded as characters.</xh:p>
   
  <tex:text>\bigskip&#xa;&#xa;</tex:text>
  
  <xi:include href="../m/no_sequencexexc.html"/>

  <tex:appendix>Sequences Data</tex:appendix>

  <xh:p>This table summarizes the naming, composition, and ligaturing of sequences:</xh:p>

  <xh:ul>
    <xh:li>In column one the character name (CHARNAME) and glyph names
    (GLYFNAME) are given along with the decomposition of the ligature
    into the base characters; in this decomposition the different
    joiners are used rather than mapping them all to `.'.</xh:li>

    <xh:li>In column two the precomposed single ligature character in
    the PUA is shown with its hex code; some ligatures do not have a
    precomposed version, in which case a `0' appears in this
    column.</xh:li>

    <xh:li>In column three the input on the upper row is the Unicode
    character sequence corresponding to the ligature sequence in the
    lower row: if the ligature is working correctly the appearance of
    the upper row should match the character in column two.  Font
    switching is used to access glyph variants.</xh:li>
  </xh:ul>
  
  <tex:text>\bigskip&#xa;&#xa;</tex:text>
  
  <xi:include href="../m/seqdb.xml"/>

  <tex:appendix>Implementation Notes on Sequences</tex:appendix>

  <xi:include href="../m/sequences.xml"/>

  <tex:appendix>Fonts for the Proposal</tex:appendix>
  
  <xi:include href="../x/fonts.xml"/>

</tex:driver>
