<esp:page xmlns:esp="http://oracc.org/ns/esp/1.0"
	  xmlns:tex="http://oracc.org/ns/tex/1.0"	  
	  xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">

  <p>The proposal is supported by two fonts:</p>

  <h2>PCSL.ttf</h2>

  <p>This is the font used for the PCSL table and other appendices in
  the proposal.  The font is remapped and augmented from
  an earlier font which was named PC24.ttf. Both PC24.ttf and PCSL.ttf
  owe a huge debt to the original work of Anshuman Pandey in turning
  Bob Englund's CDLI glyph collection into a font, and to Robin
  Leroy's work on Archaic Cuneiform Numerals.  PCSL.ttf has been
  augmented and revised extensively by Steve Tinney and currently
  contains the following components:</p>
  <ul>
    <li>12550-12686 are derived from Robin Leroy's Archaic Cuneiform Numerals font</li>
    <li>12690-12BF9 are the reference glyphs for characters proposed for encoding here</li>
    <li>F00DA-F012D are characters not proposed for encoding but listed in the OSL PUA</li>
    <li>F2000-F22B1 are glyph variants; these are also included under
    a .cvNN variant of the character of which they are a variant; in
    the PCSL table the .cvNN codes are indicated by subscript numbers
    before the glyph variants listed in the FONT column</li>
    <li>F2400-F2DA4 are unencoded characters and characters preserved
    from Anshuman Pandey's original PC font</li>
    <li>.ss04/.ss03 give some Uruk IV/III variant forms but this has
    not been done systematically; all .ss04 and .ss03 are also present
    as glyph variants</li>
    <li>.ss20 is a styleset that supports constrained width displays
    such as code charts; .ss20 only exists for reference glyphs that
    are over 1200 units wide.  The font is sized to use a maximum of
    1200 units in the y axis so no scaling needed for taller signs,
    only for wider signs.</li>
    <li>.liga entries to support the sequences as described in the
    Sequence Data appendix</li>
  </ul>

  <h2>pc25-cc.ttf</h2>

  <p>This font is designed only for use with the code chart and
  character list. The font contains no PC characters which are not in
  the proposed repertoire and uses no font features.  The scaled forms
  that are in .ss20 in PCSL.ttf are placed directly in their reference
  glyph code points in pc25-cc.ttf.</p>

  <p>The font is used in the proposal for code charts and character
  list and is also attached to the proposal PDF.</p>
  
</esp:page>
