<esp:page xmlns:esp="http://oracc.org/ns/esp/1.0" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  
<h1>Introduction</h1>

<p>This document gives an overview of the Proto-Cuneiform corpus and
character set.  Based on existing scholarship and published resources,
it also defines some principles for assessing whether a given
character should be considered encodable in Unicode at the present
time.  Applying these principles to the complete Proto-Cuneiform
character set, a proposed encodable repertoire is also provided.</p>

<p>The complete repertoire is called here the Proto-Cuneiform Sign
List (PCSL). The encodable subset and the associated documentation are
called PC25, for Proto-Cuneiform 2025.</p>

<p>The description and definition of PCSL and PC25 are intertwined,
and we do not attempt to treat them in a separate, linear way. Rather,
the PC corpus is taken as the foundation and criteria are established
for the defining the subcorpus that should be fully represented in
PC25.  Signs that occur only outside of this subcorpus are not
considered encodable, but most of the texts that fall outside of this
subcorpus are in fact fully covered by PC25 because the unencoded
characters affect relatively few texts.</p>

<p>The graphemic repertoire of the corpus is then described briefly;
this repertoire is fully represented in PCSL and subsetted for PC25
according to the principles described later in the document.</p>

<p>Another major resource for encoding PC is the collection of
published sign lists and the collection of signs based on the work of
Bob Englund that is available on the CDLI github repository.  These
lists are described and were systematically treated during the
creation of PCSL.  The individual alignments of sign lists with PCSL
are not given here but are available online.  The individual sign
lists are, however, integrated in the synoptic tabulation of PCSL
given in Appendix A.</p>

<p>The principles as well as an explanatory section on Sequences
provide the rationale for selecting characters that occur in the PC25
subcorpus for encoding.</p>

<p>In Appendix B are PC25 code charts and a listing of the character
repertoire.</p>

</esp:page>
