<esp:page xmlns:esp="http://oracc.org/ns/esp/1.0"
	  xmlns:tex="http://oracc.org/ns/tex/1.0"
	  xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
	  xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">

  <h1>Rationale for Separately Encoding Proto-Cuneiform</h1>
  <tex:text>\label{rationale}</tex:text>
  
  <xi:include xml:base="." href="../m/rationale.tex" parse="text"/>
 
  <esp:sh>ED I-II Excluded from the Proposal</esp:sh>
  <tex:text>\label{EDexcluded}</tex:text>
  
  <p>It is generally recognized that there is a group of about 400
  texts from the site of Ur which are later than Proto-Cuneiform but
  earlier than the ED IIIa corpus from Fara (Šuruppak): these are
  conventionally assigned to the Early Dynastic I-II period.  There
  are also about two dozen tablets and fragments from Uruk that are
  assigned to the same period \cite[18
  w.n.79]{LecompteVerderame2013}.</p>

  <p>Texts and signs from this period are excluded from the
  proto-cuneiform proposal.</p>

  <p>In Englund's exhaustive discussion of the Archaic texts, he
  includes this period in his concluding remarks as the 8th phase
  of proto-cuneiform:</p>

  <blockquote>8. <i>Period of late proto-cuneiform</i>
  <br/>
  Ca. 2800-2700 B.C. (Early Dynastic 1), this period is
  characterized by the earliest apparently multivalent use of
  proto-cuneiform to write Sumerian words in personal names.
  The archaic numerical systems were used, but in simplified
  forms, and the lexical lists were copied and transmitted, but
  no new lists were added. Tablets were as a rule clumsily
  formed and inscribed. \cite[215]{Englund1998}
  </blockquote>

  <p>Appearing about 15 years later, Lecompte and Verderame's
  edition of ED I-II fragments from Ur observed that there are key
  features of the writing system that depart from the earlier PC
  practices, and by analysis of both personal names and the
  contexts of the texts that they are written in Sumerian
  language:</p>

  <blockquote>We decided to follow in the transliteration the system that is
  commonly accepted for Sumerian, thus in small type and in
  accordance with the values of the signs available on the e-PSD
  website or in aBZL. We did not adopt the codes applied to the
  archaic texts from Uruk and Jemdet Nasr, although the
  transliteration available for lexical tablets in ATU 3 follows
  such a system for the ED I-II period. This choice is justified
  by the fact that the signs in the texts from Ur do not seem to
  present the same variants as their archaic forerunners: for
  example, the different shapes of E₂ cannot be classified into
  E₂~a, E₂~b...; furthermore, some signs have no variant, such as
  DU₈, which is always drawn according to a standard and well
  known shape. Second, as the language of these texts is
  undoubtedly Sumerian, it would have been unnecessary to use such
  values: instead of writing such cumbersome transliterations as
  DUB~a-LU₂-NU-ŠE₃ or EN~a-GAN~a-GI4~a, it was accordingly more
  convenient to propose directly Mes-lu₂-nu-še₃ and
  En-ḫe₂-gi₄. \cite[4]{LecompteVerderame2013}</blockquote>

  <p>Another factor which marks the ED I-II corpus as transitional
  between Uruk III/Jemdet Nasr and ED IIIa is the organization and
  structure of tablets.  In a thorough survey of these
  "diplomatics", Lecompte, based on the work of the original
  editor of the ED I-II corpus from Ur, Burrows, summarizes the
  situation as follows:</p>

  <blockquote>As Burrows has already noted, archaic texts from Ur are intermediate in nature.
  Features common with Late Uruk/Jemdet Nasr tablets include:<br/>
  – an oblong shape, half rounded sides, larger tablets having a rectangular format.<br/>
  – a reverse generally left uninscribed.<br/>
  – the presence of clauses and subscripts freely disposed apart from or into the
  columns.<br/>
  – tablets from Ur displaying rows of lines inconsistent with the usual columns; this
  clearly comes from the horizontal lines subdivided into columns observable in a
  few of the Jemdet Nasr texts.<br/>
  <br/>
  On the other hand, the ED I–II texts are forerunners to the ED III tablets in regard to
  the following aspects:
  – surface, with a rather flat obverse and convex reverse.<br/>
  – a lack of subdivision of cases similar to the Late Uruk period.<br/>
  – total expressed as gu₂-an-še₃.<br/>
  <br/>
  Other features are very specific to the ED I–II period, such as the clumsy form of many
  tablets and the random disposition of columns. \cite[142]{Lecompte2016}.</blockquote>

  <p>After discussion among the proposal authors, we have determined
  that it is preferable to establish the end of the Uruk III period as
  the cutoff for Unicode PC encoding, and to assign the ED I-II
  signiary to Sumero-Akkadian Cuneiform.</p>

  <esp:ssh>PC signs in ED I-II</esp:ssh>
  
  <p>For characters that occur only in Proto-Cuneiform and ED I-II, we
  do not propose to encode the character twice; instead, as with the
  Archaic Cuneiform Numbers, we propose to treat isolated PC signs in
  ED I-II texts as archaic holdovers.  An assignment of
  <code>Script_Extensions=Pcun Xsux</code> will be proposed for these signs in
  future documents as they are identified.</p>

  <p>Signs which occur only in ED I-II texts will be evaluated for
  encoding in SAC in the future, as will signs that first occur in
  ED I-II and recur in later periods.</p>

  <esp:ssh>Pcun and Xsux Relationships Not in Unicode Scope</esp:ssh>

  <p>The development of the cuneiform script from Proto-Cuneiform to
  Sumero-Akkadian Cuneiform is naturally a matter of considerable
  interest particularly because of the hope that better understanding
  of this development might assist in improvements in the decipherment
  and interpretation of both PC and ED texts. Scholarly discussion of
  this development can be expected to remain active and to exhibit
  ongoing shifts in perspectives and understanding
  \cite{Wagensonner2016,Selz2025}.</p>

  <p>The proposal to encode Proto-Cuneiform does not provide a
  concordance of Pcun and Xsux signs for several reasons.  One is that
  the proposal is a systematic disunification of Pcun and Xsux, which
  does not depend on the two writing systems mutually informing each
  other.  Another is that assertions concerning individual
  relationships of PC and ED signs exhibit varying degrees of certainty or
  plausibility: reducing these to a standard is currently impractical
  and may always be so.  Relatedly, a further reason is that any
  concordance provided here would inevitably require frequent updating
  of the standard.  For all of these reasons, alignment of the Pcun
  and Xsux repertoires is left as an exercise for the scholarly
  community.</p>
  
</esp:page>
